<?xml version='1.0' ?>

<!-- <!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oa
sis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"[]> -->
<!-- This comment is meant to settle gvim -->

<chapter id="conclusion">
    <title>Conclusions</title>
    <section id="full_text_search">
        <title>Full Text Search in MySQL</title>
        <para>
            When we wanted to implement searching for keywords on the 
            Lecturer and Keywords fields we contemplated how we are going
            to do it using excessive "LIKE \"%[mykeyord]%\" statements,
            or regular expressions. However, by going over the MySQL
            manual we discovered that MySQL has a full text search. (which
            was not O(n) complexity).            
        </para>
        <para>
            Due to the fact that it was an SQL extension, we hesitated to
            use it. We decided for it, because we figured out it was limited
            to one place in the code, and could easily be replaced by a 
            different proprietary method (or a standard SQL one, should the
            implementor choose to take it), assuming a conversion to a
            different database is needed.
        </para>
        <para>
            We should note that the SQL standard in itself is very limited
            and unsatistfiable, which often requires the use of proprietary
            extensions (in both commercial and Open-Source offerings) to make
            it usable. Shlomi Fish, one of the authors, even contemplated 
            starting an Extended-SQL (or X-SQL for short) super-standard,
            but so far did not advance far enough by himself to make any 
            significant progress in this area.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="mdda">
        <title>Meta-Data Database Access</title>
        <para>
            We recommend all users who work with database routinely to use
            Meta-Data Database Access Concepts. Shlomi Fish can tell from his 
            own experience.
        </para>
        <para>
            The first time he worked with an SQL database, at his first serios 
            workplace as a programmer, he queried the data by hard-coding the 
            fields across all queries. The code was eventually dumped due to
            the fact that the project heads realized that working with an 
            SQL database was too slow for the real-time constraints 
            of the application that it involved.
        </para>
        <para>
            Nevertheless, Shlomi became interested in RDBMSes and thought
            about it. Somewhat later, Shlomi decided to design the basis for
            a Perl-based Rapid-Application Development Tool. (assuming Perl 
            is not already so). To do so, he designed a database editing
            tool that could edit any table specified by an MDDA Spec, and
            using a command line or Perl/Tk user-interface. He realized that
            was compulsary as far as a RAD is concerned and from that 
            concluded that it was a good idea for many times working with
            a table is involved.
        </para>
        <para>
            In 1999, Shlomi became involved in maintaining the web site
            of the Israeli Group of Linux Users. One of the tasks involved
            was writing a web-based front-end to query a list of available
            Linux-related positions in Israel. Using MDDA, Shlomi Fish 
            implemented the database using a series of Perl scripts, and a 
            common table-wide specification file.
        </para>
        <para>
            Somewhat later it became apparent that a similar list of 
            consultants is also needed. However, Shlomi became busy with
            his studies at the time, and the job of converting the interface
            was taken by another administrator. She was able to completely
            convert the scripts by changing the specification and various
            strings spread throughout the files alone. (Later on, the 
            functionality of both copies was abstracted as a common module)
        </para>
        <para>
            She congratulated Shlomi for his "modular code" and later
            integrated MDDA into three projects she did for her workplace. 
            (it should be noted that she was a relatively inexperienced 
            programmer at the time).
        </para>
        <para>
            The lesson here is that the majority of beginning or even
            moderately experienced programmers who work with databases
            still aren't instructed to use MDDA. Shlomi does not claim
            to invent MDDA, as he is sure other people stumbled across 
            this technique earlier. Nevertheless, he believes it 
            encompasses an important paradigm, that should be conveyed
            to everyone who begins to work with it.
        </para>
        <para>
            We believe dynamically-typed languages such as Perl, Python,
            PHP, Ruby and to lesser extent Java give way much more easily
            to MDDA methods. We confess that our implementation of the 
            MDDA was not modular as it could be, mainly for lack of time for
            designing a front-end for multi-tables queries.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>


<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
mode: xml
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
sgml-namecase-general:nil
sgml-general-insert-case:lower
sgml-minimize-attributes:nil
sgml-always-quote-attributes:t
sgml-indent-step:4
sgml-indent-data:t
sgml-exposed-tags:nil
sgml-local-catalogs:nil
sgml-local-ecat-files:nil
sgml-parent-document: "zavitan.xml"
End:
-->

